Guide to the Jerome Mellquist Papers
Beinecke Rare Book and Manuscript Library
Jerome Mellquist papers
1918-1963
YCAL MSS 353
Beinecke Rare Book and Manuscript Library
9.27
(21 boxes)
Collection consists of correspondence, writings, and personal papers documenting the life and work of Jerome Mellquist. Correspondence includes letters between Mellquist and family, friends, writers, artists, musicians, and cultural critics in the United States and Europe from 1918 to 1962, with the bulk dating from the early 1930s to early 1960s. Correspondence dating from 1946 to 1948 relates chiefly to the journalist and music critic Paul Rosenfeld (1890-1946), for whom, along with Lucie Wiese, Mellquist compiled a memorial volume entitled Paul Rosenfeld: Voyager in the Arts (1948). Correspondence is chiefly in English, but letters can also be found in French, Spanish, and German. Writings include drafts of numerous short articles and essays, materials relating to published and unpublished book projects, and unsorted writings. Articles and essays relate chiefly to modern art and aesthetics. Book projects include research materials, plans, and drafts for the following: Mellquist's memorial volume to his friend Paul Rosenfeld; a book relating to French art dealer Paul Durand-Ruel; another relating to a 1962 colloquium; and one, entitled "World Art in War", on heroism in pictures. Unsorted writings and materials include short works, plays, and a novel. Personal Papers include address books, agenda books, diaries, journals, notebooks, photographs, printed ephemera, and scrapbooks.
Mellquist, Jerome
Immediate Source of Acquisition
Aquired through gifts from the Estate of Jerome Mellquist, 1963 and 1972.
Conditions Governing Access
The materials are open for research.
Associated Materials
See also Jerome Mellquist Letters to Lucie Wiese (YCAL MSS 279)
Jerome Mellquist (1905-1963)
Jerome Mellquist, born in Minnesota and educated at Carleton College (1926), Columbia University, and Yale University, was an art historian and critic. Mellquist contributed freelance criticism to journals in the United States and Europe and worked as an editor and art consultant, first as the Art Editor for the Brooklyn Eagle in 1936, and later, in the early to mid-1950s, for the American Art section of Collier's Encyclopedia and Unesco. Published works include The Emergence of an American Art (1942) and Paul Rosenfeld: Voyager in the Arts (1948).
Information taken from biographical statements in the Jerome Mellquist papers.
Scope and Contents
The Jerome Mellquist papers contain correspondence, writings, and personal papers documenting the life and work of art historian and critic Jerome Mellquist.
Correspondence includes original incoming letters and carbons of outgoing letters between Jerome Mellquist and family, friends, writers, artists, musicians, and cultural critics in the United States and Europe from 1918 to 1962, with the bulk dating from the early 1930s to early 1960s. Correspondence dating from 1946 to 1948 relates chiefly to the journalist and music critic Paul Rosenfeld (1890-1946), for whom, along with Lucie Wiese, Mellquest compiled a memorial volume entitled Paul Rosenfeld: Voyager in the Arts (1948). Mellquist solicited contributions to the volume, and some correspondence files include drafts of tributes. Correspondence is chiefly in English, but letters can also be found in French, Spanish, and German. Correspondence is arranged alphabetically, with unsorted material at the end.
Writings contains drafts of numerous short articles and essays, materials relating to published and unpublished book projects, and unsorted writings. Articles and essays relate chiefly to art criticism. Book projects include research materials, plans, and drafts for the following: Mellquist's memorial volume to his friend Paul Rosenfeld, Paul Rosenfeld: Voyager in the Arts (1948); a book relating to French art dealer Paul Durand-Ruel, entitled "The Pilot of Impressionism"; another relating to a 1962 colloquim, "Liaison des Arts"; and one on heroism in pictures, entitled "World Art in War". Unsorted writings and materials appear to include short works, plays, and a novel.
Personal Papers, arranged alphebtically by material type, include address books, agenda books, diaries, journals, and notebooks, photographs, printed ephemera, and scrapbooks. Materials date from 1928 to 1963, though the runs of agenda books and journals, dating from 1954 to 1963, provide a rich and detailed account of Mellquist's activities during the last decade of his life.
Arrangement
Organized into three series: I. Correspondence, 1918-1962. II. Writings, 1930s-1962. III. Personal Papers, 1928-1963.
Aesthetics, Modern; Art, Modern; Painting, Modern; Authors, American -- 20th Century -- Archives; Photographic prints; Printed ephemera; Scrapbooks; Authors; Durand-Ruel, Paul, 1831-1922; Mellquist, Jerome; Rosenfeld, Paul, 1890-1946; Wiese, Lucie
- Correspondence, 1918-1962; Series I; 3.34; (8 boxes)
  - "A" general, 1947-1948 (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Anderson, Eleanor, 1947-1949, undated (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - Anderson, Sherwood, 1918-1922 (Box 1, Folder 3)
    Scope and Contents
    Copies of letters to "Paul" and unidentified
  - Appleby, Theodore, 1957-1961 (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - The Atlantic Monthly, 1934-1935, undated (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - "B" general, 1947-1948 (Box 1, Folder 6)
  - Bell, Mary, 1931-1948 (Box 1, Folder 7)
  - Bessie, Alvah, 1932-1939 (Box 1, Folder 8)
  - Bing, Ilse, 1932-1933 (Box 1, Folder 9)
  - Bishop, John Peale, 1935 (Box 1, Folder 10)
  - Bogan, Louise, 1947 (Box 1, Folder 11)
  - Bogin, George, 1935-1939 (Box 1, Folder 12)
  - Brooks, Van Wyck, 1935-1948 (Box 1, Folder 13)
  - Bryner, Edna, 1946-1948 (Box 1, Folder 14)
  - Burke, Kenneth, 1947 (Box 1, Folder 15)
  - "C" general, 1947-1948 (Box 1, Folder 16)
  - Carré, Louis, 1939-1962 (Box 1, Folder 17-18)
  - Chávez, Carlos, 1947 (Box 1, Folder 19)
  - Clark, Edwin, 1951-1962 (Box 1, Folder 20)
  - Clark, Edwin, 1951-1961 (Box 2, Folder 21)
  - Content, Marjorie, 1932-1935 (Box 2, Folder 22)
  - Copeland, Aaron, 1947-1948 (Box 2, Folder 23)
  - Cowley, Malcolm, 1933-1947 (Box 2, Folder 24)
  - Creative Age Press, Inc., 1947-1949 (Box 2, Folder 25)
  - Crotti, Jean, 1958-1959 (Box 2, Folder 26)
  - Cummings, E. E. (Edward Estlin), 1947 (Box 2, Folder 27)
  - Cushing, Edward, 1937, undated (Box 2, Folder 28)
  - "D" general, 1947-1948 (Box 2, Folder 29)
  - De Koven, Jean, 1933, undated (Box 2, Folder 30)
  - Delaunay, Sonia, 1951, 1961 (Box 2, Folder 31)
  - De Silver, Margaret, 1933, 1937 (Box 2, Folder 32)
  - Dos Passos, John, 1947 (Box 2, Folder 33)
  - Durand-Ruel, Charles, 1953-1961 (Box 2, Folder 34)
  - "E-F" general, 1947-1948 (Box 2, Folder 35)
  - Frank, Waldo, 1934-1948, undated (Box 2, Folder 36)
  - Frankenstein, Alfred V., 1947 (Box 2, Folder 37)
  - Fukui, Fumio, 1934-1937 (Box 2, Folder 38)
  - "G" general, 1947-1949 (Box 2, Folder 39)
  - Gallup, Donald Clifford, 1948 (Box 2, Folder 40)
  - Gold, Michael, 1933-1935 (Box 2, Folder 41)
  - Greenblatt, Milton, 1932-1934 (Box 2, Folder 42)
  - Gregory, Alyse, 1946-1948 (Box 2, Folder 43)
  - Gunther, John, 1937 (Box 2, Folder 44)
  - "H" general, 1946-1948 (Box 2, Folder 45)
  - Harris, Roy, 1947-1948 (Box 2, Folder 46)
  - Hartley, Marsden, 1939, undated (Box 2, Folder 47)
  - Hélion, Jean, 1958-1962 (Box 2, Folder 48)
  - Herbst, Josephine, 1947-1948 (Box 2, Folder 49)
  - Hirschberg, Rudolf, 1937 (Box 2, Folder 50)
  - [Hori, N.?], 1933-1939 (Box 2, Folder 51)
  - "I-K" general, 1947-1948 (Box 3, Folder 52)
  - Joyce, Helen, 1933-1935 (Box 3, Folder 53)
  - Katz, Marjorie, 1933-1939 (Box 3, Folder 54)
  - Kazin, Alfred, 1939 May 17 (Box 3, Folder 55)
  - Kennon, Laura, 1931-1937 (Box 3, Folder 56)
  - Koenigsberg, Sam, 1934-1935 (Box 3, Folder 57)
  - Kreymborg, Alfred, 1947-1948 (Box 3, Folder 58)
  - "L" general, 1942-1948 (Box 3, Folder 59)
  - Lewi, Grant, 1935 (Box 3, Folder 60)
  - ----, Hermine, 1935, 1937 (Box 3, Folder 61)
  - Loveman, Amy, 1933-1934 (Box 3, Folder 62)
  - "M" general, 1946-1948 (Box 3, Folder 63)
  - McHugh, Vincent, 1933-1935 (Box 3, Folder 64)
  - Manteau, Anne, 1959-1961 (Box 3, Folder 65)
  - Marin, John, 1934-1950 (Box 3, Folder 66)
  - Matthiessen, F. O., 1933-1948 (Box 4, Folder 67-68)
  - Mellquist family, 1930-1939 (Box 4, Folder 69-71)
  - Miller, Henry, 1947 (Box 4, Folder 72)
  - Milo, Jean, 1951-1961 (Box 4, Folder 73)
  - Moore, Marianne, 1947-1948 (Box 4, Folder 74)
  - Mumford, Lewis, 1946-1948 (Box 4, Folder 75)
  - "N" general, 1947-1948 (Box 4, Folder 76)
  - Nin, Anäis, 1947-1960 (Box 4, Folder 77)
  - Norman, Dorothy, 1933-1948 (Box 4, Folder 78)
  - Ornstein, Leo, 1948-1949 (Box 4, Folder 79)
  - O'Sheel, Shaemas, 1948 June 23 (Box 4, Folder 80)
  - "P" general, 1947-1948 (Box 4, Folder 81)
  - Patchen, Kenneth, 1947 (Box 4, Folder 82)
  - Phillips, Duncan, 1942 September (Box 4, Folder 83)
  - Piaubert, Jean, 1954 (Box 5, Folder 84)
  - Platt, Philip S., 1947-1948 (Box 5, Folder 85)
  - Porter, Katherine Anne, 1947 (Box 5, Folder 86)
  - "R" general, 1947-1948 (Box 5, Folder 87)
  - Ransom, John Crowe, 1947-1948 (Box 5, Folder 88)
  - Robbins, Herbert, 1933-1937 (Box 5, Folder 89)
  - Rosenfeld, Paul, 1933-1934 (Box 5, Folder 90)
  - Ross, Cary, 1933-1939 (Box 5, Folder 91)
  - Roth, Rowie, 1937-1939 (Box 5, Folder 92)
  - Rudhyar, Dane, 1948 (Box 5, Folder 93)
  - "S" general, 1947-1948 (Box 5, Folder 94)
  - Selingmann, Herbert J., 1947-1948 (Box 5, Folder 95)
  - Shirakawa, Takemi, 1934-1935, undated (Box 5, Folder 96)
  - Slesinger, Tess, 1934, undated (Box 5, Folder 97)
  - Sprinchorn, Carl, 1947 June 25 (Box 5, Folder 98)
  - Staël, Nicolas de, 1949, 1963 (Box 5, Folder 99)
  - Steegmuller, Francis, 1947-1948 (Box 5, Folder 100)
  - Stieglitz, Alfred, 1935, 1937 (Box 5, Folder 101)
  - Strand, Paul, 1933 (Box 5, Folder 102)
  - "T" general, 1947-1948 (Box 5, Folder 103)
  - Taggard, Genevieve, 1939 April 9 (Box 5, Folder 104)
  - Tate, Allen, 1947 (Box 5, Folder 105)
  - Unesco questionnaire, 1955-1959 (Box 5, Folder 106-111)
  - Unesco questionnaire, 1955-1956 (Box 6, Folder 112-113)
  - Untermeyer, Jean Starr, 1947-1948 (Box 6, Folder 114)
  - "V" general, 1947-1948 (Box 6, Folder 115)
  - Van Doren, Mark, 1947 December 6 (Box 6, Folder 116)
  - Van Loon, Hendrik Wilhelm, 1933, 1935 (Box 6, Folder 117)
  - Viereck, Peter, 1947-1948 (Box 6, Folder 118)
  - Villon, Jacques, 1949-1960 (Box 6, Folder 119)
  - Warren, Robert Penn, 1947 (Box 6, Folder 120)
  - Wiese, Lucie, 1939 (Box 6, Folder 121)
  - Williams, William Carlos, 1934-1947 (Box 6, Folder 122)
  - Wilson, Edmund, 1935-1948 (Box 6, Folder 123)
  - Young, Stark, 1933-1948 (Box 6, Folder 124)
  - Unsorted correspondence, 1932-1959, undated (Box 6, Folder 125-129)
  - Unsorted correspondence, 1933-1948 (Box 7, Folder 130-134)
  - Unsorted correspondence, 1929-1949 (Box 8, Folder 135-139)
- Writings, [circa 1930s-1962]; Series II; 2.92; (7 boxes)
  - Articles and essays (Box 9, Folder 140-144)
  - Articles and essays (Box 10, Folder 145-150)
  - The Emergence of American Art, book jacket (Box 10, Folder 151)
  - Liaison des Arts material (Box 11, Folder 152-161)
  - Paul Rosenfeld: Voyager in the Arts (Box 11, Folder 162)
  - "The Pilot of Impressionism" material (Box 12, Folder 163-169)
  - "World Art in War" material (Box 12, Folder 170-171)
  - Unsorted writings and material (Box 13, Folder 172-175)
  - Unsorted writings and material (Box 14, Folder 176-179)
  - Unsorted writings and material (Box 15, Folder 180-184)
- Personal Papers, 1928-1963; Series III; 2.09; (5 boxes)
  - Address books (Box 16, Folder 185)
  - Agenda books (Box 16, Folder 186-193)
  - Banque de l'Algérie note (Box 17, Folder 194)
  - Biography (Box 17, Folder 195)
  - Bookplates (Box 17, Folder 196)
  - Business cards (Box 17, Folder 197)
  - Diaries, journals, and notebooks (Box 17, Folder 198-206)
  - Diaries, journals, and notebooks (Box 18, Folder 207-211)
  - Diaries, journals, and notebooks (Box 19, Folder 212-215)
  - Fellowship applications (Box 19, Folder 216-218)
  - Identification and membership cards (Box 19, Folder 219)
  - Passports (Box 19, Folder 220)
  - Photographs (Box 19, Folder 221-223)
  - Printed ephemera (Box 20, Folder 224-226)
  - Scrapbooks (Box 20, Folder 227-228)
- Oversize, 0.92; (1 box)
  - Scrapbook (In Series III) (Box 21, Folder 229)